Guide to the William A. Speck Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, circa 1893-1928; Series III; (13 boxes)
  - Priest, George M. (Princeton University) (Box 16)
  - Quaritch, Bernard, Ltd. (book dealers, London) (Box 17)
  - R general (Box 17)
  - Raschen, John F. L. (University of Pittsburgh) (Box 17)
  - Redpath Lyceum Bureau (Box 17)
  - Reeves, Harold (dealer in books and music, London) (Box 17)
  - Richards, Alfred E. (Yale 1898, U. of New Hampshire faculty) (Box 17)
  - Ries, H. (professor of geology, Cornell University) (Box 17)
  - Ripley, Alfred Lawrence (Yale 1878, banker, donor) (Box 17)
  - Ritti, Paul (book dealer, Paris) (Box 17)
  - Rogers, Arthur (book dealer, Newcastle on Tyne) (Box 17)
  - Rogers, John Gamble (architect) (Box 17)
  - Royal Library, Stockholm (acknowledgments) (Box 17)
  - Rühl, E. (offer of Schiller item) (Box 17)
  - Runze, Maximilian and Anita (offer of Carl Loewe manuscript scores) (Box 17)
  - S general (Box 17)
  - Sachs, R. (book dealer? NYC) (Box 17)
  - Salkeld, John (book dealer, London) (Box 17)
  - Salter, William W. (offer of autograph collection) (Box 17)
  - Sandberg, L. Oscar (dealer in coins and medals, NYC) (Box 17)
  - Savage, Henry (Yale PhD, 1924?) (Box 17)
  - Schaatts, G. (sale of autographs) (Box 17)
  - Schaefer &Koradi (book dealers, Philadelphia) (Box 17)
  - Schneider, G. (offer of Theodor Storm manuscript) (Box 17)
  - Schock, K. L. (offer of autographs) (Box 17)
  - Schoeder, Paul and Elisabeth (old friends) (Box 17)
  - Schreiber, Carl F. (Box 17)
    Speck's successor at Yale; file includes third-party correspondence and other enclosures.
  - Shiras, Winfield (Yale 1923) (Box 17)
  - Schuchard, Gottlieb Carl Ludolf (New York University) (Box 17)
  - Schüddekopf, Marie (sale of materials) (Box 17)
  - Schulte-Strathaus, Ernst (scholar, bibliographer) (Box 17)
  - Schwab, John Christopher (Yale University Librarian) (Box 17)
    File contains letters about the acquisition of the Speck Collection.
  - Shepard, Aline (College of Industrial Arts, Denton, TX) (Box 18)
  - Silbermann, B. (book dealer, Chicago) (Box 18)
  - Southern, Henry & Co. (book dealer, London) (Box 18)
  - Spaudling, John A. (Trinity College, Hartford) (Box 18)
  - Stammer, P. & Son (book dealer, NYC) (Box 18)
  - Stargardt, J. A. (book dealer, Berlin) (Box 18)
  - Steckert, G. E. & Co. (book dealer, NYC) (Box 18)
  - Steiger, E. & Co. (book dealer, NYC) (Box 18)
    File includes invoices going back to 1887, the oldest in the collection.
  - Steigerwald, Charles (Lancaster, PA; purchase of medals) (Box 18)
  - Stevens & Brown ("Library and Literary Agents") (Box 18)
  - Stokes, Anson Phelps (Secretary, Yale) (Box 18)
    File includes a letter from William Howard Taft to Stokes, 1927 March 5.
  - Stone, H. (book dealer, NYC) (Box 18)
  - Stuckenberg, Mary G. (offer of material) (Box 18)
  - T general (Box 18)
  - Taylor, Bayard, centennial exhibition, 1925 (Box 18)
  - Taylor, Bayard. Acquisition of the manuscript of his Faust translation. (Box 18)
    Correspondents include Speck, William Lyon Phelps, Peter Meagher, S. G. Raines, J. B. Francks, and Curtis Walters.
  - Taylor, Marion Lee (teacher, translator) (Box 18)
  - Thorpe, Henry (book dealer, Brooklyn) (Box 18)
  - Tiedemann, Heinrich (book dealer, Berlin) (Box 18)
  - Tinker, Chauncey Brewster (keeper of rare books, Yale) (Box 18)
  - Tondeur & Säuberlich (book dealers, Leipzig) (Box 18)
  - Trumble, Alfred (publisher of the journal The Collector ) (Box 18)
    File contains an example of Speck Brothers letter head, 1894.
  - Turner, Arthur E. (collector, London) (Box 18)
  - U general (Box 18)
  - Union Square Book Shop (NYC) (Box 18)
  - V general (Box 19)
  - Vagts, Alfred (author and historian) (Box 19)
  - Vaihinger, Hans (offer of Goethe portraits) (Box 19)
  - Van Nosdall, George A. (book and autograph dealer, NYC) (Box 19)
  - Vereinigung der Freunde des Goethehauses zu Weimar (Box 19)
  - Villard, Oswald Garrison (editor of The Nation ) (Box 19)
  - Vollbehr, Otto H. F. (incunable collector) (Box 19)
  - W general (Box 19)
  - Wadepuhl, Walter (University of Illinois) (Box 19)
  - Wahl, Hans (director, Goethe-Nationalmuseum, Weimar) (Box 19)
  - Wahle, Julius (Goethe-Schiller Archiv, Weimar) (Box 19)
  - Walters, Curtis (book dealer, NYC) (Box 19)
  - Waters, Robert (former teacher of William A. Speck) (Box 19)
  - Weg, Max (book dealer, Leipzig) (Box 19)
  - Weigel, Adolf (book dealer, Leipzig) (Box 19)
  - Weigold, Julius (sale of Goethe power of attorney) (Box 19)
  - Wells, Gabriel (book dealer, NYC; Rauch bust) (Box 19)
  - Wendte, Charles W. (clergyman, concerning papers of Charles Timothy Brooks) (Box 19)
  - Werner, Percy (lawyer, St. Louis; offer of Goethe letter) (Box 19)
  - Westermann Co. (book dealer, NYC) (Box 19)
  - White, Lucy S. (donor) (Box 19)
  - Whitney, Marian (Vassar College faculty) (Box 19)
  - Weibe, Carl (dealer in medals, Hamburg) (Box 19)
  - Williams, Frederick W. (with an account by his cousin of Bayard Taylor) (Box 19)
  - Wise, Thomas J. (forger; the correspondence is about George Borrow) (Box 19)
  - Wright, Herbert G. (University College, Bangor; topic is George Borrow) (Box 19)
  - Yale Review (Box 19)
  - Yale University Graduate School (Box 19)
  - Yale University Library (Box 19)
  - Yale University, Office of the Secretary (Box 19)
    Files contain the original agreement with Speck about bringing the collection to Yale and the records of his employment as curator.
  - Yale University Press (Box 19)
  - Yale University, miscellaneous (Box 19)
  - Z general (Box 19)
  - Zahn & Jaensch (book dealer, Dresden) (Box 19)
  - Zschiesche & Köder (dealer in medals, Leipzig) (Box 19)
- Notes and drafts for articles and lectures, circa 1870-1927; Series IV; (5 boxes)
  Files are arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  The files in this series range from short bibliographic jottings and transcriptions such as scholars necessarily made before the advent of the copy machine, to fully formed lectures. They are all handwritten by Speck, usually in pencil on half sheets of yellow paper.
  William A. Speck had no graduate degree in German literature and published little in the field, aside from the series Facsimiles and Reproductions of Unique or Rare Items from the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana (Yale University Press, six numbers, 1915-27) and an article on the Faust translator George Borrow. Yet both his correspondence and material in the notes and drafts series of his papers show that Speck was an active teacher and popular speaker. He addressed several Modern Language Association meetings, spoke at colleges and schools in Connecticut, Massachusetts, and New York State, and gave lectures before the Yale Germanics Club, church and women's groups, and the Yale library staff. The lectures and notes also include several series of talks: twenty-one essays on the portraits of Goethe; a packet of twenty-three lectures on Goethe's personality; twelve lectures on Faust, from the sources of the legend to the completion of Goethe's Faust II, and two on Faust in art; and six biographical lectures on Goethe. These series represent Speck's presentations in the two courses he offered at the Yale Graduate School, "Goethe's Personal Appearance" (1916/17 and 1919/20) and "Goethe and His Personal Influence," given first in 1917/18 and in several subsequent years. The biographical lectures on Goethe appear to have been presented almost annually in one of Gustav Gruener's courses beginning in the fall of 1919.
  - Additions to our Goetheana, 1925 (Box 20)
  - Anster, John (Box 20)
  - Bayard Taylor in Weimar (Box 20)
  - Bernays, Adolphus (Box 20)
  - Birch, Jonathan (Box 20)
  - Blackie, John Stuart (Box 20)
  - Borrow, George (Box 20)
  - Brooks, Charles Timothy (Box 20)
  - Carlyle and Eckermann (2 essays) (Box 20)
  - Coleridge and the Faustus Books of Boosey and Sons (Box 20)
  - Collecting, Collectors & Collections (notes for 4 lectures, 1914) (Box 20)
  - Den fünfzehn englischen Freunden, 1916? (Box 20)
  - [Drawings] Two supposedly lost drawings by Goethe, 1927? (Box 20)
  - English Faust translations (1833-1843) (Box 20)
  - Faust in Art: two lectures (Box 20)
    Includes: I. Faust in Art and II. Goethe's Faust in German Art
  - Faust: a lecture series (Box 20)
    Includes: 1. Faust. History and bibliography; 2. The historical Faust; [3?] The Faust-Buch of 1587; 4. Literary as distinguished from the biographical sources of the Faust Buch of 1587; 5-6. Marlowe's... Faustus and its influence on the development of the "Faust-Stoff" in Germany, parts I and II; 7. Faust dramas after Marlowe (through 1808); 8. Faust. Its Beginnings, "The Ur-Faust"; 9. Faust 1775-1790 "Fragment"; 10. Faust "The Complete First Part; 11. Faust, "Helena"; 12. Faust. The Compete Second Part
  - The Faustiana in Yale University Library (MLA lecture, 1922; 2 drafts) (Box 21)
  - Goethe – Motley (Box 21)
  - George Borrow & Goethe's Faust (MLA lecture, 1925) (Box 21)
  - Goethe and the Graphic Arts (Box 21)
  - Goethe's Personal Appearance (Box 21)
    - The portraits of the child Goethe (Box 21)
    - Goethe the boy (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse (1768-1775) (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse (1775-1779) (Box 21)
    - Klauer's bust, May's portraits (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse (1780-1785) (Box 21)
    - The Roman Goethe (Box 21)
    - The Goethe masks, the busts of Weisse and Schadow... (Box 21)
    - Angelika Kauffmann, Alexander Trippel, Klauer, Hackert (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse (1790-1800) (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse (1801-1808) (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse (1808-1810) (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse (1811-1816) (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse (1817-1819) (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse: The authentic foundations (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse (1820-1828) (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse (1821-1822) (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse (1823-1825) (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse (1826-1829) (Box 21)
    - Goethe Bildnisse (1829-1832) (Box 21)
  - Portraits of the old Goethe (Box 21)
  - Goethe's Personality (Box 22)
    - Introduction (Box 22)
    - Packets numbered 1-23 (Box 22)
    - Collection of clippings, mostly newspaper (Box 22)
  - Goethe: a set of biographical lectures (Box 23)
    - Frankfurt am Main (Box 23)
    - Leipzig – Weimar (Box 23)
    - Goethe und Weimar (Box 23)
    - Goethe in Italy (Box 23)
    - Goethe's return from Italy 1788 – the death of Schiller 1805 (Box 23)
    - Goethe (1805-1832) (Box 23)
  - [Notes on early Werther translators] (Box 23)
  - Hayward, Abraham (Box 23)
  - Holcroft, Thomas (Box 23)
  - Jameson, Anna (Box 23)
  - John Rutter Chorley and Goethe's Ideal of World-Literature, 1921 (Box 23)
    Yale Germanic Club lecture; with notes in Schreiber's hand and transcriptions in another hand
  - Dr. [N. H.] Julius of Hamburg, H. C. Robinson, and Carlyle's "German Romance" Coleridge (Box 23)
    Contains notes and transcriptions in various hands (with the record of purchase for YCGL MSS 6, folder 85, one page on notes by Coleridge on Goethe)
  - Lefevre, Sir George William (Box 23)
  - [Leveson] Ellesmere, Francis Egerton (Gower Leveson) (Box 23)
  - Martin, Sir Theodore (Box 23)
  - Melchior's Goethe medeallion (1775) (Box 23)
  - J. L. Motley on Goethe (Box 23)
  - Motley's Commonplace Book (Box 23)
  - Müffling, F. K. F. (Box 23)
    Contains 2 sets of notes on his Faust drama pf 1831 (Speck Collection Sg7.M6.831), the one, "An unedited Faust-Drama of 1831" apparently earlier than the other, which includes a complete transcription
  - Notes on rare items (Box 23)
  - Oer, Theobald von (Box 23)
  - Offene Gegend. A Fragment of the Second part of Faust, 1926 (Box 23)
  - On the portraits of the Young Goethe (1765-1775) (Library staff lecture) (Box 23)
  - Original drawing by Goethe with a short paper on Goethe and the graphic arts, 1917 (Box 23)
  - [Pens] Goethe, Johann Heinrich Friedrich Schütz, and three pens (Yale Germanic Club lecture), 1921 (Box 23)
  - Reade, John Edmund (Box 24)
  - Recollections of a literary collector (Box 24)
  - Roman portraits of Goethe (library staff lecture) (Box 24)
  - Schopenhauer as Goethe's friend (Box 24)
  - Schütz, Hermann (Box 24)
  - Schütz, Johann Heinrich Friedrich (Box 24)
  - Swanwick, Anna (Box 24)
  - Taylor, Bayard. Notes on his proposed Life of Goethe (Box 24)
  - Two old bibliographical questions answered (about early Werther translators Richard Graves and William James) (Box 24)
  - Some new English Wertheriana (Yale Germanic Club lecture), 1925 (Box 24)
  - Some English Wertheriana frequently mentioned but seldom seen (Smith College lecture), 1927 (Box 24)
  - Zerffi, George Gustavus (Box 24)
  - Drafts for early newspaper articles – in packet, 1870s-1880s (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous notes and clippings (Box 24)